<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-05T22:54:23-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Alex Cristian</title><entry><title type="html">Atlas tropezó</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/08/atlas-tropezo/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atlas tropezó" /><published>2022-08-08T05:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-08T05:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/08/08/atlas-tropezo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/08/08/atlas-tropezo/"><![CDATA[<p>Sobre la crísis de 2008.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>La semana pasada escuché <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3JmWYRkMZRo">una charla de Nomi Prins</a>, en la que hablaba sobre la corrupción general que tuvo lugar al nivel de los bancos centrales occidentales durante la crísis financiera de 2008. Esencialmente, los banqueros centrales seleccionaron a los bancos más afectados por las pérdidas sufridas en el mercado ipotecario. Les regalaron a estos miles de millones de dólares, para que puedan evitar su bancarrota - una que seguramente habría tomado con sí la mayoría de la economía occidental. Sobre esto trata, más a lo largo, el libro de Prins.</p>

<p>A primera mano, la discusión suele a concentrarse sobre <em>los culpables</em>. ¿Quienes fueron? ¿Que sucedió con ellos? Las respuestas, en este caso, son desilusionantes. Sí, hay culpables, y se sabe bien quienes son. No, no fueron condenados ni están en prisión. Sí, continuan a ser banqueros y, sinceramente, viven aún mejor que antes de la crísis; les sirvió para enriquezerse aún más, no obstante que ellos fueron también su causa.</p>

<p>Tome un momento para procesar esa información, antes de que sigamos. Me parece que es importante para poder ver con claridad la siguiente pregunta: ¿como es posible que se hayan salido con las suyas? ¿Sucederá de nuevo?</p>

<p>Creo que esa es la pregunta que, subliminalmente empezé a ponerme mientras leía el libro de Prins sobre este tema, “Collusion” - colusión. Me parece un título agresivo que, pensándolo bien, no esta completamente justificado - bueno, por lo menos, así creo yo. Un acto de colusión supone un elemento ilícito, un acuerdo al que dos entidades corruptas llegan entre sí. No creo que es lo que occurío en efecto en 2007.</p>

<p>La Reserva Federal de los E.E.U.U. fue establecida con el propósito expreso de prevenir, de cualquier forma, las futuras crísis financieras. El banco central empezó a obtener más y más poder político, especialmente después de la Gran Depresión del ´29. Ese poder fue conferido décadas antes de 2008 pero, aún así, todos quedamos sorprendidos cuando el banco utilizó ese poder para cumplir con su deber - evitar la crísis. Nos golpeó la pura injusticia de lo que aconteció - el conocimiento de que los culpables no solo que no pasarían ni un día en prisión, sino que ganarían aún más dinero por haber provocado la crísis.</p>

<p>Es mejor no discutir por ahora las razones por las que el banco central no puso condiciones a los bancos comerciales, al regalarles dinero. Acceptemoslas, por ahora, como si fueran pura verdad. De eso, resultan dos opciones: los bancos centrales pueden ayudar al mercado (de alguna manera), o bien pueden decidir hacer nada y dejar que los hechos tomen su curso. La última opción es la más clara; es lo que pasó antes de que el sistema de bancos centrales existiera - inanición a gran escala, décadas de reconstrucción y debilidad política, economica, militar mientras la crísis persistiera. Millones de fallecidos, ahora que la economía global estaba totalmente interconectada.</p>

<p>La alternativa creo yo que representa esperanza. Sí, es injusta. Sí, implica crear dinero - muchísimo dinero - con una firma de bolígrafo. Sí, proteje el capitalismo y al mismo tiempo es una medida anticapitalista, en su esencia. Pero nos compra el día de mañana. Y tal vez, el de pasado mañana. El problema va a continuar a crecer, y es probablemente insostenible - pero, por mínimo, no estamos seguros de eso. No tenemos garantías de que será un desastre. Y es lo único que podemos hacer, de todas formas. Si falla, será terrible - pero no peor que las consecuencias de no hacer nada.</p>

<p>Esa me parece que es la esencia de la crísis de 2008, y de las medidas que continuan hasta el día de hoy. Es injusto, pero, ¿cuál era la alternativa? Es probable que los bancos continuen a generar dinero de forma contínua. Las fisuras en el sistema no han tardado en aparecer - por ahora, los síntomas son solo desequilibrios sociales. Los vemos aumentando cada año; el espacio entre los ricos y la clase media, o las diferencias entre los países favorecidos por los bancos centrales y los marginalizados, a los que los bancos les demandan medidas de austeridad o intereses mucho más caros que sus economías podrían soportar. El último caso, lo vemos en toda América del Sur. Es probablemente el motivo por el que muchas más personas han empezado a tomar un interés en las consecuencias de esta crísis que, aún haber acontecido más de 14 años en el pasado, sigue teniendo un efecto sobre nuestras vidas diárias.</p>

<p>La clave de las decisiones tomadas en el pasado parece ser la esperanza. Nos ha comprado el día de hoy y el de mañana, pero el sistema ya no es uno puro capitalista. Hemos cambiado las reglas del juego y, por la mayor parte, a funcionado. Pero no todo funciona como debería. Deberemos hacer más, para equilibrar la ecuación que presentemente enriqueze a los grandes bancos comerciales, solo para que nosotros podamos vivir un día más de normalidad. El cambio, creo yo, es ya inevitable, si pensamos que vivimos en un sistema democratico y, al mismo tiempo, este problema empieza a afectar una proporción más y más grande de nosotros. La unica cuestión parece ser cuando sucederá este ajuste - ¿hoy, o mañana? Y los bancos, pues, lo saben. Logicamente, intentarán mantener el status quo por un tiempo máximo, para acumular cuanto más recursos. Si pueden, intentarán financiar a políticos, comprar cadenas de noticias que promuevan sus intereses. Pero eso no puede durar para siempre.</p>

<p>Eso es lo que me pareció interesante. Por un tiempo, me sentí indignado por el robo permitido por nuestro proprio gobierno. Pero después, me di cuenta de que hicieron exactamente lo que el Congreso decidió, hace unas buenas décadas, que deberían hacer. Y, por si nu fusiera suficiente, también obtuvieron nuevos votos del Congreso en 2008, autorizando la capacidad del banco central para tomar acción.</p>

<p>Definitivamente, ¿que hay que hacer si Atlas tropieza? ¿Le ofrecemos un hombro o le dejamos caer? Tal vez la caída lo ayudará a ser más cuidado en el futuro - pero, ¿con que precio?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sobre la crísis de 2008.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Platform domino</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/21/platform-domino/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Platform domino" /><published>2021-02-21T04:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-21T04:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/21/platform-domino</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/21/platform-domino/"><![CDATA[<p>On vendor lock-in and its long-term implications.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Modern platforms heavily rely on vendor lock-in to retain their customers.</p>

<p>What happens if a company’s core service gets neglected and abused for so long that it’s enough for customers to leave the platform entirely?</p>

<p>Normally this wouldn’t be a huge deal, since different services used to be interoperable. A megacorp’s revenue sources were siloed, so they could comfortably lose customers in one area, knowing that their other services would keep the company afloat.</p>

<p>This turns into a trap in the modern world of vendor lock-in, or that of “tightly-integrated ecosystems”, as Silicon Valley calls it. If your service is bad enough to motivate a customer to leave, they will take all of their business to someone else. You suddenly lose all revenue from that group of people; one flawed service turns into an existential problem for the entire company, no matter how mature the rest of its products are.
What makes matters worse is the difficulty of regaining customers, once something like this has happened. You will have to go against the other company’s vendor lock-in system, which almost certainly means you’re never getting your customers back (without the rival company messing up in a way similar to what you did).
If this goes on unnoticed for a critical amount of time, one could envision a scenario where a corporation loses almost all revenue because of a few failing products in its portfolio of bundled services. Vendor lock-in is a powerful business strategy, but can turn into an existential crisis very quickly, whereas traditional business models would normally allow more space for failures.</p>

<p>In this way, one product’s flaws can reflect poorly on the entire company’s offerings. To compensate, investors might want to start treating entire ecosystems as single products. Companies can no longer cushion shortfalls with their success in other areas; their business model has evolved into creating an ecosystem bubble. Could a single failing product could be enough to burst it?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On vendor lock-in and its long-term implications.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Anglocentrism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/anglocentrism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Anglocentrism" /><published>2021-02-18T13:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-18T13:30:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/anglocentrism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/anglocentrism/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>– “Nah man, it’s so simple! Just raise the minimum wage for everyone and eliminate tips that way! Problem solved.”</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>– “Wow, that’s patronizing.”</p>
</blockquote>

<!--more-->

<p>I need you to understand that this isn’t common-sense.
Someone from Finland might mention to their friend that they look fat, without giving it a second thought. In that same way, people from some parts of the world express themselves with irony, in a seamless way that is instantly understood in their society.</p>

<p>This doesn’t make you right and them wrong; that’s just the way that people grow up communicating in different parts of the planet. What does make a difference, though, is that you’re home, whereas I traveled to this country.
I’m the odd one out. That places the burden to adapt on me, but the privilege of the native - on you. Please, use it with kindness.</p>

<p>I touched a bit before on anglocentrism and, in my view, this is it at its crux. If you can’t place value on other cultures and the ways in which they live, work, grow and communicate, then at least consider recognizing what it’s like for them to change what they’ve known their entire life, in only a few years. Put yourself in their shoes and understand. And maybe, just then, respect them while they’re doing it.</p>

<p><strong>Food for thought</strong>: The above example would come across as patronizing in the anglosphere, but will be understood in other parts of the world as an act of intentionally reducing the complexity of an issue, either for pure humor or in order to pivot the discussion towards debating opposing points of view and their merits.
One interpretation creates an opportunity for growth and understanding, on a topic the first speaker could be curious to learn more about. The alternative dismisses the discussion and shuts down any hope for growth.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="society" /><category term="private" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[– “Nah man, it’s so simple! Just raise the minimum wage for everyone and eliminate tips that way! Problem solved.” – “Wow, that’s patronizing.”]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On government incentives</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/14/on-government-incentives/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On government incentives" /><published>2021-02-14T16:14:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-14T16:14:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/14/on-government-incentives</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/14/on-government-incentives/"><![CDATA[<p>What incentives might help reduce government corruption?</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Whistleblowers are an essential part of a well-functioning democracy. The public relies on people in high positions of power, who choose to jeopardize their job security in order to bring to light information of interest to society at large.</p>

<p>The incentives to become a whistleblower are few and rapidly diminishing as years go by. They often pay a heavy price for leaking confidential information. At best, they remain anonymous - at worst, they become fugitives, hunted by intelligence agencies for the rest of their lives.
The life of a whistleblower is probably most difficult in tightly controlled industries, such as those over which the government holds a monopoly. In these cases, the worker knows they’d be virtually unemployable, should they be fired. Certain occupations are so niche that one’s career would be over if they lost their current job; there’s simply no one else hiring in that field.</p>

<p>This is more obvious in some countries than others. For instance, it might be difficult for a doctor to change employers in a country with nationalized healthcare. This creates disincentives for employees that might otherwise want to blow the whistle on practices which ought to cause public alarm. Similarly, an employee at a nationalized retirement fund might be reluctant to speak out against unsustainable changes, brought about by politicians seeking to purchase the votes of retirees.</p>

<p>Competition has so far proven itself to be the organic way of counteracting this effect. Workers in the IT industry can more easily speak out against their employer, knowing they will be able to switch jobs relatively easily. The most competitive fields sometimes also tend to be the ones with the highest degrees of transparency.</p>

<p>Another possible solution would be that of institutional guarantees. This approach has been largely ineffective in providing cover for whistleblowers, due to the ease with which institutional protections can be unwound. A government may, in case of force majeure, bend its own rules in order to silence a whistleblower, either by convicting them of a crime or retaliating in some other fashion. On the other hand, a company cannot easily prevent its competitors from hiring a whistleblower.</p>

<p>Assuming transparency is beneficial to society, it would seem to follow that most public services should rely on the private sector as much as possible. It would be a straightforward way of addressing systemic corruption, which often thrives in an environment lacking whistleblowers. In societies with corrupt governments, bad actors frequently exploit the inaction of their peers in order to reap massive profits - which they then leverage to amass even more power. This creates a toxic cycle of corruption that is difficult to interrupt once triggered.</p>

<p>Checks and balances are necessary for any system to efficiently perform its functions. So far, many “big governments” have repeatedly proven their inability to police themselves. The solution probably is to avoid placing any trust in an organization’s capacity to self-regulate.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="politics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What incentives might help reduce government corruption?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On nationalism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/30/on-nationalism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On nationalism" /><published>2020-09-30T04:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-30T04:33:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/30/on-nationalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/30/on-nationalism/"><![CDATA[<p>The idea of a Europe of nations leads down a dark path of nationalism.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Firstly, the entire concept of national identity is reductionist towards our true human spirit. There are no “true” Frenchmen, Spaniards, Italians or Romanians. These are all artificial constructs that we have conjured up around arbitrary criteria that change every century. We have all migrated throughout the continent, many of us speak multiple languages and have been exposed to humanity’s great thinkers, whatever their origins may have been. We draw on the rich cultural achievements of our civilization on this planet; humanity is our identity, nothing less.</p>

<p>When I think of this, I remember so many acquaintances throughout the years that moved from country to country during their childhood. What would their “national identity” be? What would mine be, for that matter? In my first 20 years of life on this Earth, I spent about a third of it living in one country, and the other two thirds living in two other countries. Where do I belong? National identity politics are unclear - on purpose. In this way, there will always be an “other” on which to blame your mistakes, a scapegoat to bully and persecute until you can find another, more convenient target.</p>

<p>If national identity is nothing more than an useful illusion, what is sovereignty? In the most literal sense, it is the cornerstone of democracy - the idea that the people are sovereign over their destiny. In practice, this term is all too frequently hijacked to mean “national sovereignty”. It is something entirely different, in my opinion, which simply refers to the notion of protecting some particular form of bureaucracy, variants of which we have established at every national level. These are governments protecting their jobs, yes, but most importantly watching out for their <em>power</em>.</p>

<p>In any European supranational federation, there’s no question that our democratic institutions will be perpetuated and expanded. Areas where we have little oversight will need to be simplified, so that power always returns to the people in as direct of a way as possible. A European federation does not pose a problem of sovereignty; the people are still in control. We merely recognize that <em>a lot</em> more binds us to each other than to our nations. Those standing to lose from this transformation are often those opposed - nationalist organizations, that would be ruined if we finally recognized that there is more to a human being than their nationality.</p>

<p>Ultimately, the final argument towards a European federation is made by the very basis for government in human existence. Nationalist leaders would have us think that our identity revolves around regional politics, hymns, historical prejudice and - in my opinion, most hilariously - borders that have changed after almost every major European conflict, of which our continent has had plenty. They preach that this is the culture that we must preserve and defend from those outsiders who seek to dilute it. It sounds absurd to even write it on paper.</p>

<p>Government exists to serve the people. And the people, time and time again, make it very clear what their identity truly is. You see it when so many of our neighbors choose life partners of different nationalities than their own. When high-schoolers choose to study Asian languages or culture in their spare time, or perhaps read American literature on civil rights and the equality of man - even though their national curriculum has perhaps a different focus, as it was in my case. National governments coerce their citizens into thinking that they need them, that they enjoy being limited by them and have no needs outside of this very well defined area of culture they deem “their own” and, thus, acceptable to embrace in society.</p>

<p>We must recognize our new reality. Realize that we are no more bound to one nation than we are to the organized crime from our hometown, that happens to make the nightly news. Or to the corrupt politicians that invariably infest the generous ranks of all our European national governments, with duplicated functions and responsibilities that have been modified <em>just enough</em> so that it leaves the ordinary citizen frustrated and confused. No, we associate our identity to the great thinkers, artists and scientists of our civilizations. They bind humanity together in a way no inward-looking demagogue can hope to match. And once we take that step, look inwards and ask ourselves who we are - there will be no turning back.</p>

<p>The time of populism is ticking. Our love for each other will always prevail.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="opinion" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The idea of a Europe of nations leads down a dark path of nationalism.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Punct Palid Albastru</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/25/punct-palid-albastru/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Punct Palid Albastru" /><published>2020-09-25T17:36:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-25T17:36:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/25/punct-palid-albastru</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/25/punct-palid-albastru/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve had some trouble finding a Romanian version of Carl Sagan’s Pale Blue Dot. Despite being only a book excerpt, it is by far some of his most widely recognized work in popular science. Below is my best attempt (and work in progress) at translating it to Romanian:</p>

<!--more-->

<blockquote>
  <p>Privește din nou acel punct. Acolo este aici. Acolo este acasă. Acolo ne aflăm. Pe el, fiecare om pe care-l iubești, pe care-l cunoști, de care ai auzit, fiecare om care a fost vreodată, și-a trăit viața. Însumarea bucuriilor și suferințelor noastre, mii de religii încrezătoare, ideologii, doctrine economice, fiecare vânător și culegător, fiecare erou și laș, fiecare creator și distrugător de civilizații, fiecare rege și țăran, fiecare tânăr cuplu îndragostit, fiecare mamă și tată, copil visător, inventator și explorator, fiecare profesor de morală, fiecare politician corupt, fiecare “superstar”, fiecare “lider suprem”, fiecare sfânt și păcătos din istoria speciei noastre a trăit aici - pe un fir de praf atârnat de o rază de soare.</p>

  <p>Pământul este o foarte mică scenă într-o vastă arenă cosmică. Gândește-te la râurile de sânge vărsate de toți generalii și împărații pentru ca, în glorie și triumf, ei să poată deveni stăpâni temporari asupra unei fracțiuni a acelui punct. Gândește-te la nenumăratele cruzimi comise de locuitorii unui colț al acestui pixel asupra altuia, cât de frecvente neînțelegerile lor, cât de nerăbdători în a se omorî, cât de pătimași în ura lor.</p>

  <p>Atitudinea, importanța noastră propriu imaginată, amăgeala unui rol privilegiat în Univers, toate sunt puse în cumpănă de acest punct palid de lumină. Planeta noastră este o pată singuratică în marele întuneric al cosmosului ce ne înconjoară. În această beznă, în imensitatea din jur, nu există niciun indiciu cum că ajutorul va veni din altă parte pentru a ne salva de noi înșine.</p>

  <p>Pământul este singura lume cunoscută capabilă să găzduiască viață. Nu există niciun alt loc, cel puțin în viitorul apropiat, spre care specia noastră ar putea migra. Să vizităm, da. A ne așeza, încă nu. Ne place sau nu, pentru moment rămânem pe Pământ.</p>

  <p>Se spune că astronomia este o experiență care întărește modestia și clădește caracterul. Nu există, poate, mai bună demonstrație a prostiei vanității umane decât această depărtată imagine a micii noastre lumi. Mie îmi evidențiază responsabilitatea noastră de a fi mai binevoitori unii cu ceilalți și de a păstra și prețui punctul palid albastru, singurul cămin pe care l-am cunoscut vreodată.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>– Carl Sagan, Punct Palid Albastru (“Pale Blue Dot”), 1994</p>

<p><img src="http://localhost:4000/assets/images/paledot.png" alt="Pale Blue Dot - Earth as seen from Voyager I, 6 billion km away" class="wide_img" /></p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pale_Blue_Dot">Imaginea atașată</a> a fost transmisă de proba spațială Voyager I, îndreptată către Pământ la o distanța de aproximativ 6 miliarde de kilometri depărtare. Pe 14 Februarie, 1990, semnalul acestei imagini a călatorit cu viteza luminii timp de aproximativ 5 ore și 33 de minute pentru a ajunge de la Voyager la noi, pe Pământ.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve had some trouble finding a Romanian version of Carl Sagan’s Pale Blue Dot. Despite being only a book excerpt, it is by far some of his most widely recognized work in popular science. Below is my best attempt (and work in progress) at translating it to Romanian:]]></summary></entry></feed>